James E. Roberts Papers VHP2006/12
CCSU Veterans History Project
James E. Roberts Papers
Bulk, 1943-1945
1943 - 1945, 2006
VHP2006/12
CCSU Veterans History Project
4.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of James E. Robert as he served in the U.S. Army during WWII in Europe. The collection contains video of an oral history interview, an excerpt of publication about the 104th infantry division, and few photographs.
Robert, James E., 1924 -
Biographical/Historical note
James E. Roberts enlisted in the United States Army after finishing his sophomore year at the University of Illinois. He decided to enlist so that he could choose the branch of service he would serve with. He attended basic training at Fort Bragg, NC, and then went to Rutgers College, NJ for a semester while he awaited an assignment. In August of 1944, Roberts arrived on the Belgian/German border and became part of the 385th Field Artillery Unit, 104th Infantry division, where he was an ammunitions handler. His job was to load and unload the ammunition for the Howitzer his unit used in combat. Roberts recounts his experiences in Europe, including the crossing of the Rhine river, interacting with German civilians, witnessing serious battle fatigue, exposure to British prisoners of war, the liberation of the Nazi death camp, Nordhausen, and meeting up with the Russian army. Roberts was discharged from the Army in December of 1945, and returned to the University of Illinois to finish his education.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army. Infantry Division, 104th. Field Artillery Battalion, 385th.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 104th.; Belgium; Fort Bragg (N.C.); Germany; Howitzers; Nordhausen (Concentration camp); World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Germany
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/12.I
  - Interview synopsis, Nov. 24, 2006; VHP2006/12.I.1
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/12.II
  - Excerpt of "Timberwolf Tracks: The History of The 104th Infantry Division 1942 - 1945", July 1946; VHP2006/12.II.1; 10.0 pages
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/12.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/12.III
    - James E. Roberts, December 1946; VHP2006/12.III.1
    - James E. Roberts at the time of interview, 2006; VHP2006/12.III.2
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/12.IIIb
    - Oral history interview with James E. Roberts, Nov. 24, 2006; VHP2006/12.IIIb.1; Muzzulin, Kristin (Disk DVD VHP2006/12, Box VHP Interview 2006)